OK, let's get started.
Cool.
So as a recap of
last week, we talked
about multi-task
reinforcement learning
and how we might want to
have reinforcement learning
agents not learn just one task,
but multiple different things
that might correspond to
multiple different reward
functions.
And we saw that we can
formulate an aggregated MDP that
encapsulates all of the
different tasks, where you now
are augmenting your state with
some sort of task descriptor,
like a prompt or a goal or just
an index corresponding to what
the agent should do.
And the way that
this worked is we'd
sample some task, run the
policy in the MDP for that task,
sample another
task, and so forth.
And we would then
get a policy that
could be able to successfully
achieve high reward
in a number of different MDPs.
Or another way to
view it, as single,
aggregated MDP with
this augmented state.
This is going to be a little
bit different from meta-RL.
So we'll see some differences
here later in this lecture.
And we also somewhat
briefly talked
about goal-conditioned
reinforcement learning.
And it could just
be simply viewed
as a special case of multi-task
reinforcement learning,
where each task is trying
to reach a goal state.
And the task descriptor
corresponds to that goal state.
And so if your states
are images, for example,
then now you'll be
passing as input
to the policy, both the current
image and the goal image.
And you'll be trying to
reach that goal image.
Or if your state, for
example, is a vector,
you'll be passing
in two vectors.
And the task is trying
to reach some goal state.
And you can construct
different reward functions,
if you have discrete states
or continuous states,
as some sort of, did
you reach that goal
or reach close to that goal.
And one of the
things that's kind
of nice about this
goal-conditioned formulation
of reinforcement learning
is that you can actually
do it in a self-supervised way.
You don't need task descriptors.
You don't need a
different set of tasks
that you've manually defined.
You can just use a bunch
of different states
as the tasks themselves.
And a lot of different tasks
can be formulated as goal
reaching tasks.
One thing to note here is it
can be pretty hard to train.
But you'll be experimenting
with a simple, goal-conditioned
reinforcement learning
setting in your homework.
OK, so for today we're going
to be talking about meta
reinforcement learning.
And specifically, we'll be
talking about what that problem
statement looks like and
a class of meta-RL methods
that I like to refer to as
black-box meta-RL methods.
We'll start to get into
what these methods look like
and also some of the
challenges that they face.
So what's the problem?
Why do we care about meta-RL?
Why not just do vanilla RL?
So say that you're
trying to figure out
how to operate an espresso
machine that you've never
used before.
If you wanted to do
that, well, first,
if you wanted a robot
or a reinforcement
learning agent to do
that, it would probably
take a lot of data,
a lot of attempts
to try to figure out
how to make coffee.
Because it's a pretty
complicated task,
lots of different
steps involved.
You have to do the
steps in sequence.
And also, the reward signal that
you get for this sort of task
probably isn't going
to be super detailed.
But as a human, if you
were to attempt this task,
probably if you had a
little bit of instruction
or some previous
experience making espresso,
then you could probably learn it
in minutes, or maybe even less
than a minute.
So if you think about
reinforcement learning, this gap
between how quickly a
human could learn something
and how slowly it would take a
reinforcement learning system
to learn it, this is
rather unsatisfying.
And if we think about what is
the difference between a person
and a reinforcement
learning system,
one of the big
differences is that people
aren't starting from scratch.
People already know how to move
objects around with their hands.
They might already know how
to make coffee in other ways
or with other machines.
And they can leverage
that experience and also
some notion of semantic
knowledge of what
to do if someone tells
you to pick up a cup
and put it somewhere,
or to turn a knob.
And I can leverage that
previous experience in order
to solve this problem
really, really quickly,
compared to training a
reinforcement learning system
from scratch.
And so experience
with similar tasks,
other espresso-making machines,
either espresso making
on other machines or just
general motor control,
following instructions,
that sort of thing
can be very useful when
trying to solve a new task.
And I mentioned this as kind of
an example with espresso making,
but this framework of
not starting from scratch
is really general.
So it applies to
robotics problems
where you're facing
a new environment
or facing a new task.
But it's also really faced by
many reinforcement learning
systems.
As another example, say you
want to solve a challenging math
problem that you
haven't solved before.
If you have experience solving
previous math problems,
then you can use that
to more quickly solve
a new problem, because you've
learned some sort of strategies
that you might be able to
apply to the new scenario.
OK, we're framing
this question of,
can reinforcement learning
algorithms leverage experience
from previous tasks in order
to learn a new task with less
data and less experience?
In many ways, this
problem is thought
of as a transfer
learning problem, where
we want to transfer
knowledge, information,
experience from previous
tasks to new tasks.
And there are a few
different formulations
and a few different
problem settings
that the research community
has thought about.
One is a fairly standard,
a fairly simple setup
where you learn one task and
then want to learn a new task.
And you can just, for
example, train on one task
and then fine-tune
on the new task.
And notions of fine-tuning that
we use in supervised learning
are also applicable to
reinforcement learning settings,
where you could fine-tune
a Q-function to a new task,
or fine-tune a
policy to a new task.
Although, for this to
work well, the tasks
need to be quite
similar to each other.
We also talked about
multi-task learning.
And you could also use
multi-task learning for transfer
to new tasks.
And in particular, if your
prompt shares some structure,
if it's just like a
task 1, task 2, task 3;
transfer is going to be harder.
But if it's something that
has a lot of structure,
like pick up a water
bottle, pick up a phone,
pick up a pen, and so forth;
then you might actually
be able to have
things transfer what's
called zero-shot, without
any new experience
at all, simply by passing
that prompt to the system
and having it act
according to that prompt.
And then meta-learning is
often concerned with, instead
of zero-shot transfer, something
that's called few-shot transfer,
where with a little
bit of experience,
a few examples or a
few trials of a task,
can you adapt to that task?
And essentially the difference
between multi-task learning
and meta-learning is that
it accounts for the fact
that we're going to
be trying to adapt
with a small amount of data.
And it does that during the
original training process.
And another way of
thinking about this
is that instead of having
the task descriptor be
a prompt or an index, the
task descriptor might actually
be a dataset itself,
like a set of trials
that you're going
to be adapting to
in the context of some policy.
Another word for this is
sometimes in-context learning
or few-shot learning.
Now, for this to work, for
the first scenario to work,
you must have very similar
source and target tasks.
Whereas, in some ways, things
get a little bit easier
and a little bit harder
for number 2 and number 3.
They get easier in the
sense that you no longer
have to have an
extremely similar task.
You, instead, just need to
have a distribution of tasks
and be similar to that
distribution, such
that conceivably, the new task
that you're trying to solve
should be within the
distribution of the task
that you've seen
during training.
It gets a little bit harder
because you do actually
need a number of training tasks,
not just a single training task,
in order to get
effective transfer.
OK, before we jump into
meta-RL, let's just
look at a couple few-shot
learning examples outside of RL,
and then go back
to the RL setting.
So actually, I
picked this example
so that it's not trivial.
There's other test data points
that are much, much easier.
Cool.
So that's the essence of a
few-shot image classification
problem, where you have a
small number of data points.
And your goal is to
classify a new data point.
And typically, if you were to
train from scratch on just six
images, you'd have
no hope of being
able to learn a
classifier, especially
on high-dimensional images.
But the way that
meta-learning works is you
can construct other tasks for
the machine learning system
to solve that have
a similar structure,
like other image
classification tasks,
train it to be able to take
as input a training dataset
and a query image or a test
input, and then predict a label.
And basically, constructing
each of these few-shot learning
problems as a data
point themselves.
Now, another example of
few-shot learning outside
of reinforcement
learning is in-context
learning in large
language models.
And what this looks like
is, here's just one example.
There's lots of examples of
different tasks you could do.
In this case, the goal is, given
a sentence that's poor English
input, like, "I eated
the purple berries,"
output good English input like,
"I ate the purple berries."
It gives it, in
this case, I think
four or three different
examples of input-outputs.
This is the training dataset.
And the goal is for
a new input to be
able to predict a good
output for that example.
So here's another example of
a few-shot learning problem.
And again, language
models get things that
look like this during training.
One thing that's a little bit
special about language models
is that this sort of
in-context learning,
you don't explicitly set up
your training dataset exactly
to match all of this.
And it turns out that a lot
of the statistics of data
on the internet
leads to this ability
to react to these few-shot
examples effectively.
This is actually
just a base model.
I think this is from GPT-3.
And so even without any
additional supervised training,
you get something like this.
It's not perfect.
It doesn't work all the time.
But this is another example
of few-shot learning.
And then in each
of these examples,
you can think of
the goal as trying
to train this model that
takes as input a training
dataset and a new
example x, and makes
a prediction for that
example, based on both x
and on the training data.
Yeah, so the question is, in
in-context learning in LLMs,
typically you achieve
this sort of model,
this few-shot learning
through prompting,
by putting the
dataset in a context
or as part of the
prompt into the model.
Is that also how it
works in meta-RL?
Generally, yes, we're
going to be looking
at that case in meta-RL.
There are actually other methods
where you can accomplish this,
actually, with gradient
updates as well,
or with something that looks
like nearest neighbors.
The most successful method in
meta-RL looks like prompting.
And so that's what we'll
be talking about today.
Now, let's look at
a meta-RL example.
So, say that we want
to navigate mazes.
And so our goal is, we
want to solve a new maze.
And we're an agent
that's in this maze.
We don't get to see.
We actually don't even
see this top-down view.
Maybe we just have a
first-person perspective.
And our goal is, because this
is a reinforcement learning
problem, it's not just
about outputting a label.
It's actually also about
collecting experience
in the environment.
And so the goal
is, we'd like to be
able to very quickly solve a
reinforcement learning problem.
And we'll frame this as
collecting a very small training
dataset of one episode
or a few episodes.
In this case, it's
exploring the maze,
trying to find
where the goal is.
And it starts in the middle
right here, explores over here.
And it eventually goes
to the goal, right here.
And after we explore,
we'd like to be
able to have a policy
that is able to solve
the maze, in this case,
just with a single episode
of experience.
And again, if you were
to do this sort of thing
from scratch that
tries to use just
a single episode of
experience to get
a policy that can
solve the task,
this would be very, very hard.
And instead, the way
that meta-RL frames
this is by trying to
construct examples
and trying to construct a
set of training environments
that facilitates this
kind of fast adaptation.
Now, in comparison to the
supervised learning scenarios,
like I mentioned,
we're now going
to be faced with this
exploration problem.
We're not just given
a training dataset
and then make a prediction
based on that training dataset.
We're actually constructing
the training dataset ourselves
through exploration.
And we need to figure
out how best to trade-off
between exploring in the
environment versus being
able to then solve the task; and
how much time we should spend
exploring versus
trying to exploit what
we know about the environment.
So this is our goal.
This is what we'd like to
be able to do at test time.
We'd like to be able to
quickly learn a new maze.
Then, to set our agent up for
success at meta-training time,
before we try to
adapt to a new maze,
we'll try to learn how to
efficiently explore and solve
many other MDPs
that are related.
In this case, they can be other
mazes like this, and so forth.
And these are each of
the tasks that we'll
be training on in order
to adapt to a new maze.
Cool.
The other thing, one
key assumption here
is that you need to have--
these new MDPs
can't be completely
different from the MDPs
that you saw before.
And the way that we can
think about that is we
should have some sort of
distribution over tasks.
And these new MDPs that
we're trying to adapt to
should be within the
distribution of tasks
that we saw during training.
Maze navigation is one
example of a meta-RL task.
There's lots of other
scenarios as well.
So one useful scenario
that we've seen in robotics
is being able to
adapt very quickly
to different terrains, different
slopes for legged robot systems.
This is actually a really
small legged robot,
but it's also applicable to
larger legged robots as well.
And sometimes you
might actually be
training on different
environments in simulation
and then adapting
in the real world
as just another environment.
You could also have
object manipulation
as different tasks, as well,
in manipulation scenarios.
And then there's also a number
of language modeling scenarios
where this is quite applicable.
One example where
meta-RL has been relevant
is adapting to different users
with different preferences,
where you give examples
of the kinds of responses
that they want in context.
And we'll also later see an
example in reasoning as well.
Yeah, so the question is,
what is the key difference
between this sort
of meta-RL approach
and transfer learning
where you're training
and then fine-tuning?
And there's a couple
of ways to view it.
One is that during
the training process,
you're actually explicitly
optimizing for transferability.
You're optimizing
for the ability
to adapt with a small dataset.
And as a result of that, you
can get much faster transfer.
You can use a much
smaller dataset.
And there are examples
of, if you use fine-tuning
versus if you use few-shot
in-context learning
or few-shot
adaptation, you can get
much more efficient transfer.
So you get much
greater efficiency.
And the way that you
get that is by providing
the algorithm with a number
of different training tasks,
rather than just one training
task that you're feeding off of.
So slightly more
formally, we've talked
about multi-task
learning, where you
try to solve multiple
tasks at once.
You might try to transfer
to a new task from that.
But you're not optimizing
for transferability.
With transfer
learning, you're trying
to solve some target task
after solving some source
task, typically by fine-tuning.
Whereas, in the
meta-learning problem,
we have experience from
some training tasks
and we want to very
quickly solve a new task.
And in the reinforcement
learning scenario,
these tasks are going to be
MDPs, each with their own state
space, action space,
dynamics, reward.
And we see meta-learning
and supervised learning.
And also there's a nice
analogy between the two,
where the main
difference with meta-RL
is this exploration challenge.
And then diving
into some notation
here, we can view the
meta-RL problem as basically,
with a small amount
of experience,
be able to learn a policy
that can solve the task,
and also to be able to collect
this experience itself.
And so this training
data, there's
two different variants
of the meta-RL problem.
In the first case, this can
correspond to multiple rollouts
from some exploration policy.
And instead, you
could also consider
this to be just actually a few
time steps from your exploration
policy.
There's a bit of a continuum
between these two scenarios.
You might want to
be able to adapt
both online with
a few time steps,
and with more and more episodes,
with basically a growing
dataset, but writing
it explicitly
as two different things
here to make it clear
that there are some problem
settings where you want
to adapt really quickly
online within an episode,
and other scenarios
where you're caring
a lot more about multiple
trials of experience.
The last thing that
I'll mention is
I've been writing it as an
exploration policy and a task
policy.
There are some scenarios
where you might train these
and these might be
separate networks.
There's other
scenarios where these
could share parameters and
basically be the same network.
So they don't necessarily
need to be separated
like they are on this slide.
And then the last
thing is, insofar
as we're learning
this policy that's
conditioning on a
training dataset,
you can view this as
a task identifier.
And from that
standpoint, we're then
more in a setting that looks
like multi-task learning.
So the question is, when
I say that the test has
to be in distribution
compared to the training task,
does that mean it has
to be the same as one
of the training tasks?
Or can it be a bit different?
It can be a bit different.
And we'll see examples where
it is different as well.
So let's talk about how
to address these problems.
So the good news is that there's
a very conceptually simple way
to address this general
problem statement.
The bad news is that it can
be challenging to optimize,
in practice.
And we'll talk about some of
those challenges in a bit.
But conceptually,
we can essentially
train a sequence model.
It could be a
transformer, any sort
of neural network with memory,
a recurrent neural network.
And use this, where
basically everything that's
being passed into this policy
corresponds to the experience
that the agent has collected.
And so you're basically
conditioning your policy
on this training dataset.
And then having a policy output
actions based off of the data
that it's seen so
far in that MDP.
And then training the
sequence model policy
across all of the set of
training MDPs that we have.
So here, this is
the current state.
This sort of context
or training dataset
is going to get larger
over time as we collect
more experience in a given MDP.
Now, a question for you.
There are a couple
of differences
between this and simply
using a recurrent policy
in a standard RL setup--
or using a sequence model
in a standard RL setup,
like using a transformer.
Does anyone have
thoughts on what
are some of the
differences between what
I'm starting to talk about here
and simply using a sequence
model as your policy
in a standard RL setup?
Memory.
Yeah, so typically in RL,
we often don't use memory.
And here we're using memory.
So that's one thing.
But compared to if we had used
memory in a standard RL setup,
what else is different here?
Yeah, so one thing
that we're doing here
is we're actually passing the
reward as input into the memory.
And that's a little bit
different in the sense
that you're actually
using reward information
from the current MDP in order to
try to get better at the task.
This also means that
actually at test time
or when we're trying
to adapt to a new task,
we're also going to
be using the reward.
And in RL settings,
oftentimes we
don't necessarily assume that we
have the reward when we're just
deploying our policy.
So that was one main difference.
Any other differences?
Yeah, so the question is,
why are we also not passing
as input the actions?
You can pass as
input the actions.
It depends on, if your policy
is mostly deterministic,
then information
about past actions
could be stored in
the memory as well.
Because you were predicting,
you generated those actions.
And so in those cases, you
don't need the actions.
If you have a more
stochastic policy,
then that sampling process won't
be necessarily in the memory.
And in those cases, it's good
to pass as input the actions
as well.
Right, so the note was that the
states and actions might not be
the same for different tasks.
And so one of the
things that's different
here is we're actually training
this model across MDPs.
And so you might have a
different state and action
space.
You might have
different dynamics.
And so one of the big
differences compared
to standard RL is that actually
we're training this across MDPs.
And there's going to be
differences in states, actions,
dynamics, and rewards
across those MDPs.
Cool.
There's actually also
one other difference.
But the first thing
that we talked about
is, we see that the
reward is passed as input.
You might also be
passing as input actions.
And this is trained
across multiple MDPs.
And that's quite different
from the typical reinforcement
learning setup.
Now, the second thing
that's also different
is that your memory
is also going
to span across multiple
episodes, potentially.
If you're trying
to actually learn
not just within an episode,
but learn across episodes, then
rather than having your current
policy simply have memory
within an episode, you
will be maintaining
any sort of hidden state
or any sort of memory,
not just within your episode,
but across multiple episodes.
Maybe I'll leave this up
here in case it's useful.
In terms of the algorithm,
what this looks like is,
we will sample a task or an MDP.
So maybe let's call this MDP Ti.
And then we're going to
run our policy in that MDP
for multiple episodes.
So let's say, run pi in our
task or MDP for n episodes.
So this is rolling
out this right here.
And it's going to have memory
across those N episodes.
And then, optionally, if we're
using an off-policy algorithm
with a replay buffer, then
we would store the episodes
in a replay buffer.
And then lastly, we're
going to update our policy
to optimize the rewards.
And so we will be updating pi.
And specifically, we are
going to be maximizing
the sum of rewards, like
the typical RL objective,
but it's going to be across
all of the tasks in our task
distribution.
So we'll have some sum over
tasks i, in some mini-batch,
and then also the
expected sum of rewards.
So this would be an
expectation under our policy
of the sum of rewards
over different time steps.
Now, this is a pretty
simple algorithm.
It looks a lot like
reinforcement learning,
where simply the main
thing that's different
is that we're going to be
doing this optimization
across multiple MDPs.
And our policy will have memory
across a set of episodes.
Usually N, usually this is
going to be pretty small.
Because if it was large, if
it was like 1,000 episodes,
it's going to be hard to store
that in the context of a model,
just because your memory will
start to increase substantially.
So what that looks like is
you have this neural network.
It has multiple episodes.
And then you'll be rolling
it out for multiple episodes,
taking actions, and then you'll
start collecting for a new MDP.
So you'll cut your
memory when you
start to collect for the
new MDP that you've sampled.
So you sample a task, roll
out the policy for n episodes.
In this case, n equals
2 in this diagram,
under the dynamics and
reward function for that MDP.
Then, store in
your replay buffer.
Oftentimes, you'll have a
replay buffer for each task.
And then update your policy to
maximize the discounted return
for all tasks that
you've collected for.
And then repeat this
process in order
to continuously
get a policy that's
better at doing this
in-context adaptation.
Yeah, so that's a good question.
So the question is,
does it know that it's
starting a new episode, like
at this position right here?
You could use a
position encoding.
In practice, you're also
going to probably have
a discontinuity in your state.
And so you might
just be able to see
that your current state is very
different from the past state.
And that might also tell it.
But yeah, you could
have some sort of token
to also tell it that
it's a new episode.
The question is, are
we randomizing S1
across the different episodes?
When you're rolling
out the policy, when
you start a new
episode, that will
be a different sample from the
initial state distribution.
And so, S1, I guess it's
maybe a little confusing.
S1 here might be
different from S1 here.
S2 is very likely different
from S2 here, and so forth.
Cool.
And then the outcome
of this is you'll
have a policy that should be
able to adapt across episodes
with experience
from those episodes.
And it should be
able to, on its own,
actually decide on the best
exploration/exploitation
trade-off.
And the best
exploration/exploitation
trade-off is going to depend
on the number of episodes
that you give it.
If N is 2, then it
has two episodes
to maximize rewards as
quickly as possible.
And if and if it
needs to explore,
it'll explore as
quickly as possible.
If N is a little bit
larger, then you've
given it a little
bit more budget--
it still wants to explore
quickly and efficiently,
if it can, because then it
can get higher rewards later.
But it might have slightly
more budget to explore.
And so one of the things that's
pretty cool about this, when you
optimize this whole
thing end-to-end,
is that it will make
decisions on whether or not
to explore or to exploit.
And it'll make those
decisions in a way
that's informed by whatever
gets it the highest reward.
Then, after this
training process,
after you've trained
it on multiple MDPs,
you can actually then roll
out your policy in a new task.
So at test time, you will
then give it a new task.
So you're in some new MDP, Tj.
And you can take the
policy that was trained
and roll it out in that MDP.
So roll out pi in that MDP
with those states, actions,
and rewards, and so forth.
And so sample new task,
roll out that policy.
You want to roll this
out for up to N episodes.
If you roll it out
for longer, all bets
are off, in terms
of what it might do.
You could also have a
variable number of episodes
that you use during
training, if you
want it to be able to handle
variable numbers of episodes.
But yeah, this would be like
for N episodes or for up to N
episodes.
Cool.
So in terms of actually
implementing this,
there's a few
different architectures
and optimizers you could use.
So you could use a vanilla
recurrent neural network.
Some of the first works on meta
reinforcement learning did this.
And they used algorithms.
This is, I think, before PPO
existed or was introduced.
They used an algorithm
that's somewhat
similar in nature, in terms
of the assumptions, as PPO.
There's is also a paper that
before transformers were really
popular, used self-attention
and also 1D convolutions.
You can think of it
sort of a transformer.
It optimized this.
And you can actually
note that they do also
pass the actions as input
in this particular scenario.
One other thing, we'll talk
about this a bit more later.
But you can also, instead of
using a transformer or an RNN,
you could also use a feedforward
network and then average across,
average the embedding.
This is sometimes
called a deep set.
And it has its own benefits.
It's actually pretty
computationally fast,
because you can
parallelize everything.
And also, actually,
it's surprisingly
expressive for what it can do.
So let's look at some examples.
So we'll look at this example
that was using something that's
a bit like a transformer.
And they were
trying to learn how
to visually navigate a maze--
specifically, new mazes that the
agent had never been in before.
They trained it on
1,000 small mazes.
And they tested it
on held-out mazes
that the agent
hadn't seen before.
And they tested it actually
both on small mazes
and on large mazes.
So this is actually
a scenario where
they were able to see some
extrapolation to tasks
that were outside of
the distribution of what
it was trained on.
So this is what it looks like.
So this is at test time.
And you can see that
the agent, it just
is exploring around
this environment,
looking for where the goal is.
It only gets these
images as input.
And on the right, we can see
the trace of the exploration.
So it started in the
middle, explored over here,
it explored down here, and
eventually found the goal.
And then after that
exploration episode,
we still have memory from
that previous episode.
And using that memory,
it's able to then
be able to go
directly to the goal,
based on this
experience in that maze.
So watching that again, whoops.
This is the first episode.
And so this is the first episode
of rolling out this policy.
It's choosing to explore
because it doesn't know
where the goal is in this maze.
It also doesn't know
the layout of the maze.
And so we see it explore here.
And then in the
second episode, it
chooses to go
straight to the goal
because it decided that
it already explored
the extent of the maze.
Here's an example
in a larger maze.
So the agent starts over here.
And it explores in the top
part, doesn't see the goal.
It realizes that
this is a dead end.
It doesn't need to
explore it further.
And then it ends up
seeing the goal here.
And then after that, it
goes straight to the goal
after that first episode.
And so in this training
example, N equals 2.
So they trained it just to be
able to explore and exploit
after two episodes.
Cool.
And then quantitatively, they
looked at the average time
to find the goal in
both the first episode
and the second episode.
They compared to using a random
policy, which occasionally does
happen upon the goal,
and using an LSTM
architecture and this more
self-attention and convolution
architecture.
And they found that with
the small mazes, even
within the first episode, they
were able to do a lot better
than random.
That's because it's actually
exploring efficiently and then
eventually often
finding the goal.
And then it's able to
find the goal faster
in the second episode,
after learning
where the goal is and about
the maze in the first episode.
We also see that it does
significantly better
than a random agent
in the large mazes.
And in both cases, using the
self-attention architecture
is better than using an
LSTM architecture, which
is another memory architecture.
Yeah, so the question is, is
the reward to find the goal?
And if so, why is it optimized
to find it as fast as possible?
So the reward is
to find the goal.
I don't remember the exact
structure of the reward.
It's optimized to
find it quickly.
There's a couple of
ways that lead to it
to optimize to find it quickly.
In this particular
case, I believe they're
using discounted rewards.
And so the discount factor,
instead of being like this,
you're optimizing for
discounted rewards.
So there's a discount
factor right there.
And the discount
factor is not 1.
It's probably like 0.95 or 0.99.
And so that objective
will be higher
if you get the reward
sooner rather than later.
Yeah, so the question is, what
is passed as input to the model?
Yeah, exactly, so it's video
from the previous episode,
the actions from the
previous episode.
Basically, everything up
until the current time step,
which is any previous
episodes and everything
so far in that episode.
So it's all of the video frames
and then also all of the actions
and all of the rewards as well.
Yeah, so the question is,
where in the algorithm
are we exploring exploration
versus exploitation?
And, here, it basically
all comes down
to this objective
for both of them.
And the insight is that
the agent doesn't know much
about the task.
It doesn't know.
Well, depending on the
training tasks, in this case,
it doesn't know
what maze it's in.
It doesn't know the structure of
the maze and that sort of thing.
And so actually it's not
able to get high reward
until it starts to
explore, until it finds
where the goal is, for example.
And so by optimizing just
end-to-end for reward,
you're incentivizing it to--
it's not going to get high
reward without exploration,
essentially.
Yeah, we will talk about
that soon in a few lectures.
But yeah, there's
lots of problems here.
Because when your policy
is bad and you're not
getting good rewards, it ends up
being very difficult to figure
out a good policy.
Yeah, so the question
is, instead of
doing what we're doing,
could we just do regular RL
and then do test-time training?
So in some ways, language
models with recurrence,
it depends on how you
view it, but in some ways
you are already doing
something that kind of looks
like meta-RL, if it has memory.
It basically has the
ability to adapt,
depending on the task
that you're giving it.
And then one important
component is,
if you're doing
test-time compute,
you're allowing it to actually
think through the problem.
Now, test-time compute
is a very broad term.
So on the next slide, we'll
talk about how meta-RL is
relevant for test-time compute.
So let's talk about that now.
So say that we're solving
different math problems.
This is the canonical language
model example, especially
for test-time compute.
And one example
of a math problem
is trying to show
this inequality.
This is actually the same, I
think, possibly the same math
problem that [INAUDIBLE]
showed in his lecture.
And in some ways, trying
to solve this math problem,
you can think of it
in some ways as an MDP
itself, in that there's
different strategies that you
might try to take to
solve this math problem.
And you don't know, a priori,
which strategy is going
to help you solve that problem.
Where do you start?
Do you try to, for example,
do you guess and check?
Do you try to eliminate terms
in the equation and so forth.
And ideally, you'd
be able to explore
those different strategies and
then produce an answer based off
of the best strategy.
So DeepSeekR1 is
a language model
that uses test-time compute in
order to solve math problems.
And if you give R1 different
math problems to solve,
if you give it a hard problem,
it thinks for a while.
At some point, it cuts
off its test-time compute
because it doesn't
want to be thinking
for too long for the user.
And then it outputs some
explanation for the user.
And then also, if you give
it a really easy problem,
like 2 plus 2 equals
question mark,
it actually also kind of thinks
through what the solution might
be and then gives a step-by-step
explanation for the answer.
And so this is something that
is clearly somewhat wasteful
to do, probably, unless this is
somehow a challenging problem.
And so you can actually
use this notion of meta-RL
to try to optimize
for test-time compute.
And if you know
that you're going
to be doing test-time
compute at test time,
then basically bring that
into the training process
and encourage the model
to efficiently use
that test-time
compute, efficiently
explore different
strategies, such that,
ideally, on easy
problems, it is trying
to output an answer as
quickly as possible.
And for harder
problems, it's thinking
as much as it needs, including
possible exploration,
until it then tries to exploit
and give an explanation.
And so this paper here was
a paper that explored that.
They found that when they were
trying to explicitly optimize
for effective use of
test-time compute,
they were able to get higher
performance with the same number
of tokens, and also actually
reduce the number of tokens
needed to get the same
performance so that you aren't,
for example, using up a ton
of tokens on simple problems.
So that's a use case
of meta-RL or ideas
for meta-RL in language models.
Now, a quick
digression, and this
will actually lead us
into a different way
of thinking about meta-RL.
So we've talked about
multi-task policies
where we condition
on a task descriptor.
So maybe we want
a robot to stack
in different
locations or a robot
to walk in different directions.
And we've talked about policies
that take as input experience
and then generate actions
based off of that dataset.
And if you were to think about
how this relates to multi-task
learning policies, one
way to think about it
is that we're just doing
multi-task learning,
but now this data is
our task identifier.
And this is something that
actually changes within a task.
So the analogy is not perfect.
It's not actually
fixed for a given task.
You can think about it as
conditioning on the task,
insofar as experience tells
you what the task you're
trying to do is.
Cool.
And if you think about
goal-conditioned policies,
rewards, you can
also view meta-RL
as kind of a generalization
of goal-conditioned policies.
Because there's a set of MDPs
that are goal-reaching MDPs.
And then there's a
broader set of MDPs
that are reward-maximizing MDPs.
And then the other way
to think about this
is instead of trying to
generalize to new goals,
you can think about meta-RL as
trying to adapt to new tasks
with a small amount
of experience.
And this would be the difference
between zero-shot generalization
and the goal-conditioned
case and k-shot
generalization with k
episodes or k time steps
in the meta-RL case.
So we've talked
about how we could
view the experience as the
task descriptors [INAUDIBLE]
the prompt, essentially.
But there's actually
another way to look
at it, which is that if we think
about this policy with memory
that has the past memory
and then our current policy,
if we were to think about what
information is being passed
right here to the policy;
this information is presumably
information about the task.
And specifically when zi
isn't part of the state,
there's ambiguity about what
MDP you're trying to solve.
And you're using that
experience to try to identify
the MDP that you're in.
And you can think
about it as the policy
needs to infer the task.
It needs to infer specifically
some sort of latent task
descriptor from its experience.
And so another way
of looking at meta-RL
is something where you
are using your experience
to infer what the task
is, and then conditioning
your policy that's acting
at the current time
step on your current
estimate of what the task is.
So you can think
about it essentially,
as meta-RL is trying to explore,
to infer this unknown task,
and then perform the task.
I see.
So you're asking, because we're
going to be inferring the task
identifier, why don't we just
give it to the learning system?
Yeah, so the main
reason is that if we
don't have a compact
way of describing
the task that the
agent is doing, then
it may actually be challenging.
If we don't have a good
way to represent it,
then we're not sure what
to pass into the policy.
And if we don't have a good
way of representing it,
we can always resort
to just using an index,
saying this is task 1, this
is task 2, this is task 3.
But if you do that
and then at test time
you say this is
task 100, it's not
going to be able to
generalize in that scenario
and do anything about that task.
Whereas, conditioning
on experience
is something that
could generalize,
where it can actually be able
to use the more continuous space
of states, rewards,
and so forth in order
to figure out a new task.
So it comes down
to representations.
And you could view this as
learning a z representation,
like learning like a
continuous vector that's
representing our tasks.
Now, in multi-task RL,
we talked about how
if you formulate
some state space,
that it corresponds
to the original state
space and the z vector.
Then, you get this
aggregate MDP.
And so the result of this
is still an MDP, just with
a new state space
and new dynamics
to account for this
new state space.
And so there's a question
of, for meta-RL, is there
an aggregate MDP?
And this would be for meta-RL.
And in this case, we're not
providing zi in the state.
And so actually,
inherently, it's
actually partially observed.
You don't actually
know what the task is.
You're trying to explore and
figure that out from experience.
And so there isn't
actually an aggregate
MDP that you can think about.
Instead, if you wanted
to try to aggregate it
into a single
decision process, it
would have to be a partially
observable MDP, or POMDP.
And it's actually a
special kind of POMDP,
where we talked
about before, where
you have some partially
observable Markov decision
process where you can't actually
observe S. And you have actions.
And instead of observing S,
you observe some observations
that are some function of S.
That would be the
general POMDP case.
One thing that's a little bit
special about the meta-RL thing
is the only thing that you can't
observe is what the task is.
And so it's basically a
POMDP where this hidden state
space can be defined as the
observation and the task
identifier.
And if you can infer the task
identifier from experience,
then you can essentially
view it as a way
of trying to infer the
underlying state space as a way
to solve the POMDP.
So this is basically
another way of looking
at the meta-RL
problem, as basically
like a partially observable
Markov decision process.
Now, there's a meta-RL method
that we actually talked about.
I showed an architecture diagram
that was actually explicitly
trying to output z's, And it
was actually outputting some
distribution over z's.
Because at the very
beginning, you actually
don't know what z is.
You have some kind of prior
belief over what z is.
And then as you get
more experience,
you're going to have a better
and better estimate of what z
is.
And so if you represent
a distribution
over this kind of latent
task representation,
then you can do cool
things with that.
And we'll see that in a bit.
So this particular algorithm is
looking at continuous control
problems where different
tasks correspond
to walking in
different directions,
running at different velocities;
and also different physical
dynamics-- so being able to
adapt when the friction is
different or the inertia of
the robot system is different.
The other thing was
that everything,
what we saw before was using
a PPO-style algorithm, which
is somewhat off-policy
but not very off-policy.
It's more on-policy than
off-policy in some ways,
because it's not using a
replay buffer of past data.
And with meta-training
algorithms,
you can adapt really,
really quickly.
But the training process
might be really slow
if your base algorithm
is fairly on-policy.
And so as a question,
hopefully, this
should be a
straightforward question,
if your base algorithm for
updating the policy at step
four, if that's an
off-policy algorithm,
do you expect that to be more
or less efficient than if you
used an on-policy-based method?
Yeah, more efficient.
So if you're using
a replay buffer
and using that replay buffer to
update your policy with memory,
that should be a lot more
data efficient during
this meta-training process.
At test time, when
you're adapting,
the efficiency is
going to be similar.
So this is just talking
about the efficiency
for actually training this
in-context learning system.
And so if you actually look at
the curves over this training
process right here, the amount
of data that you need in
order to meta-learn in
these kinds of systems.
You can see that
in blue, if we're
using an off-policy algorithm
with a replay buffer,
it's a lot more data
efficient, learns
a lot more quickly
than RL2 and ProMP.
I want to say all three
of these are using base RL
algorithms that are more
on-policy and more like PPO,
for example.
Yeah, so the question is, can I
elaborate on what specifically
is in the replay buffer?
Well, so each replay buffer will
have a sequence of episodes.
Basically, each thing
in the replay buffer
will be a sequence of
episodes from a given MDP.
And that includes the states,
the actions, the rewards.
And when you optimize
this, oftentimes, you'll
have a different
replay buffer per task
so that you can sample a
task here and then optimize
the reward for that task using
the memory from that trajectory.
Typically, the buffer,
instead of just storing
states and actions, you're
storing full trajectories
together because you're going to
be training a model with memory.
And you need to be able to
provide that trajectory as input
to the policy.
Cool.
So summary so far, we've talked
about using these models to be
able to adapt to new MDPs.
They're general.
They're quite expressive.
And there's also a variety of
choices in the architecture.
One thing is they're
hard to optimize.
Because actually it
needs to figure out
how to adapt from data.
And there's lots of
different input features
here that you could try
to pay attention to.
And the model has to figure out
what about those input videos
that you're passing as input
for the maze navigation
is useful when you're then
trying to exploit and learn
a policy.
Because you're passing in
so many things as input,
it's such a big model, it
can be hard to optimize
for that reason.
And it can also be hard to
optimize from an exploration
standpoint, which we'll
talk about right after this.
And then the sample efficiency
of the meta-learning process
is going to be inherited from
whatever optimizer you use
in this last step right here.
And so if you use something
like vanilla policy gradient,
it'll be extremely
data inefficient.
If you use something
like PPO, it'll
be more stable, but
still fairly inefficient.
If you use something
like SAC, it
will be probably a
lot more efficient,
although you might need to
tune the hyperparameters more.
So now let's talk a
bit about exploration.
By exploration, I
mean exploration
in context,
exploration when you're
trying to explore a new task.
What we've talked
about so far is
trying to optimize
end-to-end for exploration
and exploitation, with respect
to the final sum of rewards.
Simple, in principle,
it could actually
yield the optimal
exploration-exploitation
trade-off because you're
optimizing directly
for the sum of rewards.
And that's really, really nice.
But it can be a really
challenging optimization.
And let's talk about
why that's the case.
So let's look at
a running example.
So say that you have some
robot that looks like this.
And the robot needs
to find something.
And there are some
hallways that the robot
might need to go
down in order to try
to find the thing that
it's trying to find.
And different tasks correspond
to different locations
of the object that
it's trying to find.
So in one task or
in one scenario,
it might be all
the way over here.
In another scenario, it might
be over here, and so forth.
And to help the robot
out a little bit,
we're going to introduce
one other thing, which
is that there's going to be
some piece of paper over here.
And that paper actually says
where the object is in words.
Maybe it's trying to find
a replacement light bulb
or something like that.
And it says, the light bulb
is in the fourth hallway
at the end.
OK, so here's our robot.
Here are the hallways.
Different tasks
correspond to navigating
to the ends of the
different halls.
And we have some information
about where to go.
And if we look at
that, information
will be in the state about where
the reward is for this task.
Now, how do we actually
learn how to explore?
So say that we were trying
to collect trajectories
and trying to learn
how to explore such
that we can get good behavior.
Let's start with the scenario
where we sampled a task.
And maybe the task was to go to
the end of this hallway right
here.
And say that we
actually just got lucky.
We collected a trajectory
that just went straight
to that reward.
Now, in some ways,
that seems good
because we got reward for that.
And so that gave us some reward.
And that's optimizing
the objective
that we care about ultimately.
But the thing that's
bad about this
is that the robot got lucky.
And it doesn't actually know how
to repeat that in the future,
because it didn't actually
explore any other alternatives.
And so the way that
we can view this
is if it goes to the end
of the correct hallway,
it'll get positive reward.
But the context leading up to
getting that positive reward
doesn't actually look
different than any other task.
It went through here.
And there's nothing
that differentiates
what it did there, which was
like zero reward, zero reward,
than if the task, for
example, had been to go here
or to go here.
And as a result, it didn't
actually learn how to explore
and it didn't learn how to use
exploration information in order
to solve the task.
And so this trajectory
might not actually
be very helpful for
learning how to explore
and learning how to exploit.
Now, let's say that we had
a different trajectory.
So we're exploring.
And let's say that the
agent, instead of doing that,
it maybe sampled the same task.
And it went to the
end of this trajectory
and then continued,
didn't see that,
and then went to the
end of this trajectory.
So that would be good, in the
sense that it has experience
that ruled out one task.
And then it got rewarded
for a different task.
And so it's going
to be teaching it
something about an exploration
strategy that works.
The downside is that exploration
strategy is quite suboptimal.
Because it would have been a
lot more efficient to first look
at the instructions and then
go to the correct position.
And so it's somewhat
good, somewhat bad.
It provides signal on a
suboptimal exploration
and exploitation strategy.
And so it's perhaps better
than the first trajectory
that it did, but
still not ideal.
Now, let's consider
a third trajectory.
Say that we are again collecting
data for the meta-RL process.
And let's say that
the agent decided
to look at the instructions
and then just stay and watch
the instructions.
Does anyone have
thoughts on whether that
would be a useful trajectory or
not for the learning process?
Yeah, exactly.
So it did something
useful, but it doesn't
get any reward for that.
It only gets reward if it
did that and then went here.
And so that's also not going to
be very useful for the learning
problem.
And basically, in the
problem like this,
you're only going to actually
be learning something
useful about how to explore and
exploit if you successfully did
the proper exploration behavior
and then did the exploitation
behavior.
And if you do them
in separate episodes,
then you're not actually
getting good learning signal.
And that means that you have
this kind of sample complexity
where you need to actually get
lucky and do both of the two
things at the same time in
order to get signal that
helps you learn the problem.
So basically, it's hard to
learn how to explore and exploit
at the same time.
Another example of
this is say that you're
trying to learn how to cook.
You have data in
previous kitchens.
Your goal is to then be
able to quickly learn
how to cook in a new kitchen.
Now, in order to
learn how to cook,
you need to find
the ingredients.
And if you haven't
yet figured out
how to find the ingredients
because you have
bad exploration,
then you can't learn
how to cook because you don't
have the ingredients with you.
And then you're going
to get a low reward.
And then also, if
you don't yet know
how to cook because you
haven't collected experience
on that, then regardless
of the exploration you do,
you're going to get low reward.
And so you have this
chicken and egg problem
between learning how
to explore and learning
how to solve the task
using that information.
And so there's another way to
view this coupling problem where
exploration and
execution or exploitation
depend on each other in order
to be jointly successful.
So then the way to view
end-to-end training
is that it's great
in that you can
learn this optimal trade-off.
But it can be
extremely challenging
if you have a hard exploration
problem, because you
need to figure out how to
explore and exploit and get
learning signal that way.
The question is, is the
ultimate challenge here
that the reward is sparse?
So it's true that if
you had a dense reward,
you'd be in a much
better place, basically,
because you wouldn't
really have to explore.
Well, you wouldn't
have to explicitly take
actions to explore.
And this really comes
down to a problem
when exploration is hard.
If exploration is easy,
this really isn't a problem.
Because you no longer have
to solve both exploration
and exploitation.
You only have to
solve exploitation.
So there's a couple
solutions to this.
And we'll start to talk
about one solution today.
And then on Friday, we'll
talk about more solutions.
So the second solution, I'm not
going to go into complete detail
on how these work.
But one solution here is,
instead of optimizing just
for end-to-end reward, you can
add in auxiliary exploration
objectives to encourage it
to try to actually figure out
something more meaningful
about the task.
And one approach
here is to use what's
called posterior sampling,
also called Thompson sampling.
And the way that
this works is that we
talked about an algorithm
where you're trying
to infer what the task is.
And if you've collected
some experience so
far and you've inferred some
distribution over your task--
in this case, zi is now
some latent representation,
it's not a representation
that's known--
then what you could
do is you could then
sample from this
distribution and then act as
if that was the correct task.
So if you have this
task inference procedure
and then you also have a policy
that, given an estimate of z,
is able to generate actions,
then what you can do
is you can sample a z from this
distribution and then sample
from this policy.
This starts to decouple
the problem a little bit.
Because if you have policies
that for a given z do the task,
then you would basically
learn an exploration strategy
that is trying to go down the
different corridors to find
the solution.
So as an example,
this is actually
a problem that looks somewhat
similar to the corridors, where
you get a sparse reward if you
reach one of these circles.
And the different circles
correspond to different tasks.
And in this case, we've
sampled this task right here.
And first, we sample a z
from our prior over tasks.
We haven't collected
any data yet.
So we sample z.
We then run our policy based
on those different z's.
And we get exploration
based on these.
And then we use that to
infer what the task might be.
And so now we know that
the task is probably
either over here or over here.
And so now you'll
collect trajectories
that are lighter in color that
are like this one, this one,
and going over here.
And then once you've actually
collected this trajectory,
then you should actually have
a much narrower distribution
over the task because you
get positive reward here.
And so then your z distribution
will be narrowed out here.
And you'll execute your
policy according to those z's.
And so that's one approach for
addressing this exploration
problem--
basically, learning this latent
representation over tasks
and then sampling
from that distribution
and acting according to
your policy for that task.
So there's some scenarios
where this is great
and scenarios where
this is not so great.
Does anyone have thoughts on
when this sort of sampling
might be bad, like
what sort of MDPs
this might not work well in?
"If you have a
large action space."
That could contribute.
Although, it isn't just having
to do with the action space.
Because if you have a dense
reward and a large action space,
you'd be probably OK.
So if these are out
of distribution,
certainly things
will be problematic.
But even in
distribution, there's
scenarios where this exploration
strategy will be really bad.
Yeah, so one scenario where
this might work poorly
is if you start to
see some reward,
but there might actually
be an even better reward
in another scenario,
you might start
to exploit a little
bit too early.
Although, it won't rule out
those higher reward scenarios
if it knows that
there are other tasks
that might have higher rewards.
So I guess the scenario
that I was thinking
of where I think
that this can be
quite bad is actually a lot
like this scenario right here.
So the strategy that
posterior sampling
will learn in this
scenario is, instead
of looking at the
instructions, it's
instead going to go down
each of the hallways
and try to find the reward.
Because it's trying
to explicitly explore
by executing policies
corresponding
to different tasks.
And this will be especially bad
if the hallways are very long.
So if the hallways are
really, really long,
take days to traverse,
then what it's going to do
is it's going to spend
days going down one of them
and then figuring out that
it's not the right one.
And then spend days
going down another one,
rather than trying to
seek out information that
might tell it about what to do.
So, for example, if these
goals are very far away
and there is some
sign that tells you
what the correct goal is,
then this is a bad strategy.
Now, if that sign doesn't
exist, then it actually
would be a good strategy,
because you have to go down
those different corridors.
There's a couple
of other approaches
that we can use as well
that include [INAUDIBLE]
intrinsic rewards
that try to encourage
it to visit new states, and also
trying to visit states that help
you distinguish the
dynamics and reward
models for different tasks.
So we try to collect data
so that our model of rewards
and states are accurate.
And with this sort
of approach, you
could actually get
exploration strategy
that looks a lot more efficient,
that looks something like this,
compared to posterior
sampling, that's
trying to just sample the
different trajectories
for the different tasks.
There's also scenarios
where this might be bad,
if there's lots of distractors
or really complex state
dynamics.
But unfortunately, I
don't have too much time
to go over that now.
So these sorts of
approaches are easier
to optimize than end-to-end.
A lot of them have some
principle behind them,
but they can be very suboptimal
in certain environments.
And it kind of depends on the
environment or the domain.